God, that is the most beautiful engagement ring ever!
這真是世上最美的訂婚戒指
You should know. You bought, like, a billion of them.
你一定很識貨，你買過一大堆
You didn't get one.
但是你沒有
-Tonight's the big night. -How you gonna ask her?
-好，就是今晚了  -你要怎麼進行？
We're gonna go to her favorite restaurant.
保證完美 我會帶她上她最愛的餐廳
I'm gonna get her favorite champagne. She'll know how expensive it is.
我要送她一瓶她很喜歡的香檳 那她就知道有多貴了
When the glasses are full, instead of proposing a toast, I'm gonna propose.
然後等酒斟好了，我不會敬酒 我會向她求婚
It sounds perfect!
好棒喔
-You'll mess it up. Let me do it. -I won't mess it up.
-你會搞砸 讓我來吧  -我才不會搞砸
-lf she says no,can I have the ring? -She won't say no.
-要是她說不，戒指可以給我嗎  -她不會說不
If.
要是
-Sure. -What about me? I want it too.
-沒問題  -那我呢？我也想要
-She won't say no. -I'll let you borrow it.
-她不會說不  -我再借給你
Hey,Monica.
-Give it. -It's gone.
-還給我 -吞下去了
Phoebe.
菲比
Hey,Monica!
We're practically kissing.
我們在接吻喔
The One With the Proposal
本集播出：「驚喜的求婚」
rainystar壓制iPod-MP4
Anyone free tonight? My boss is hosting a charity event for kids.
晚上有人有空嗎？ 我主管要主持救助貧童慈善會
The more people I bring, the better I look. Monica? Chandler?
我帶越多人去越有面子 摩妮卡？錢德？
We can't go. We're going to dinner. Remember?
摩妮卡和錢德不能去 我們要去吃飯，記得嗎？
-Oh,my God. I'm so sorry. -What's the big deal?
-天哪，真抱歉  -幹嘛這麼激動？
I get mad when Rachel doesn't remember where we're going.
我只是很氣瑞秋不記得 我們要去哪裡
Where are you going?
你們要去哪裡？
-How about you guys? -Open bar?
-那你們呢？ -酒品免費？
-I think so. -I can do that for the kids.
-應該是  -我可以為孩子們喝酒
I'll come. I'm making money. It's time I give some back.
那我也要去 我現在有收入 也該回饋社會了
You could give back the money you owe me.
你也可以把欠我的錢還給我
Okay. Have a benefit.
好啊，你辦義賣啊
Ross, can you go to a charity event tonight?
羅斯 你晚上可以參加慈善晚會嗎？
I have plans with Elizabeth.
不行，我跟伊麗莎白有約
You're already doing your part for the kids.
你已經在為孩童貢獻心力了
It's our last night before she leaves for camp. To be a counselor.
再過幾天她要去夏令營 去當指導員
I have a question. All jokes aside, where is this relationship going?
羅斯 我問你 撇開笑話不提 這段感情要往哪裡走？
All jokes aside? I didn't agree to that.
等等，撇開笑話不提？ 我可不同意
-Do you see this as long-term? -I don't know.
-你認為你們可以長久嗎？ -我不知道
-You are 12 years older than her. -Who's counting?
-你比她大12歲喔  -誰會去算？
Well,she is. She's this many.
她會，她才這麼大
Ross, she is really young.
羅斯，她真的很年輕
Does everyone feel this way?
等等，你們都這麼認為嗎？
-Yeah,sort of. -Sorry.
有一點 抱歉
I thought you were just making jokes. I had no idea.
我以為你們只是愛開玩笑 我都不知道
You guys are wrong. Yes,there is a chronological age difference.
不過你們都錯了 沒錯，我們是有年齡上的差異
But I never notice it, because she is very mature.
但是我都感覺不到 為什麼？因為她很成熟
It doesn't matter what you guys think. I'm dating Elizabeth, not you.
況且我根本不在意你們的看法 跟她交往的是我，不是你們
Not what she said last night.
她昨晚可不是這麼說的
See,now,he could date her.
他配她就夠幼稚
Will you marry me?
你願意嫁給我嗎？
Hey, you marry me.
嫁給我
-What's going on, little elves? -It's the big night. We wish you luck.
-怎麼了，小精靈們？ -今晚很重要，我們想祝你好運
-You have the ring? -In my pocket.
戒指帶了嗎？ 就在口袋裡
-Phoebe. -Wha..?
菲比
Will you guys get out of here? This is a surprise.
麻煩你們出去 我想給她驚喜，她會看出來
Yeah,you guys. Get out of here.
沒錯，快出去
Hey,guys.
你們好
-You look beautiful. -Thank you.
-你好漂亮 -謝謝
What's going on?
怎麼了？
We're just really...
我們只是…
excited about this charity event we have to go to.
要參加慈善晚會覺得很興奮
-Here. -Thank you.
給你 謝謝
-So, what's going on here? -Well,this is a silent auction.
-現在是怎樣？ -這是一場不喊價拍賣會
They lay the stuff here. You write down your offer.
要賣的東西都在這裡 你寫下競標價
Then the highest bid gets it.
出價最高的就是得主
I know what a silent auction is. What's going on with your hair?
我知道什麼叫不喊價拍賣會 我是說你的頭髮怎麼了？
-Why? -No,it's nice.
-怎麼說？ -不是啊，很好看
Nice to see you. So glad you brought someone.
歡迎 你帶了一位朋友來
Someone? I brought people.
一位？我帶了兩位
Phoebe, this is Mr. Thompson. He's the head of my department.
菲比，這位是湯普森先生 他是我的部門主管
-And I also brought my friend Joey. -Shrimp toast!
-我還帶了我的朋友喬伊… -蝦子吐司
You know, I don't know where he is.
我不知道他在哪裡
I hope you'll bid.
希望你會參加競標
Actually,I was about to bid on this lovely trip to Paris.
我正打算投標這趟巴黎之旅
-Nice choice. Good luck. -Thank you.
-有眼光，祝你好運  -謝謝
Okay.
好
Twenty dollars.
20元
Shut the door! Shut the door!
把門關上，把門關上
-What's going on? -Guys are throwing water balloons.
-怎麼了？ -對面的男生在朝我們丟水球
Call the cops. That's what I did to kids in my building.
你們得報警 我都這樣對付我家那棟的小孩
No, it's a water balloon fight. We started it.
這是水球仗，是我們挑起的
I stopped by to see if you wanted to see this play tonight.
聽我說 我來問你晚上要不要去看戲
It's excellent. The director is..
這齣戲應該很棒，導演…
-Who drank all the kamikazes? -Nobody. We put them in here!
-誰把神風特攻隊都喝了？ -沒有，在水球裡
You want some?
你要嗎？ 不要
-Could I talk to you for a second? -Yeah,sure.
我可以跟你講一下話嗎？ 當然可以
So this play, what do you think?
所以你要去看戲嗎？
-It's gotten great reviews.. -Attack!
-它的劇評很好…  -攻擊！
-Put your balloons down! -You put your balloons down!
-放下水球 -你們才放下
Everybody put their balloons down!
統統都把水球放下
Now,this is a nice suit!
這可是高級西裝
If you'll excuse us...
請你們出去一下
I would like to speak to Elizabeth alone for a moment.
我要單獨跟伊麗莎白談談
Whoa,Liz. Your dad's a bummer.
麗莎，你爸好掃興
Our next item is the romantic trip to Paris.
下一項拍賣品是巴黎浪漫之旅
It goes to Emil Alexander with a high bid of $2300.
由艾彌爾亞歷山大 以2千3百元的高價得標
So close!
只差一點
Guys,look. Got me some drinks.
你們看，我拿了幾杯酒
-What are you doing? -Open bar.
-你在幹什麼？ -不用錢嘛
Well,now it's an empty bar.
你會把人家喝垮
You can't stand anyone else enjoying themselves, can you?
你就是見不得別人開心對吧？
Finally,our biggest item.
最後是今晚的最大項目
The 22-foot Gentleman's Daysailer sailboat.
22尺豪華帆船
The winning bid was a whopping $20,000.
得標金額高達2萬元
I won.
我贏了
That was my guess.
那是我猜的
-What? What? What? -I guessed $20,000.
-什麼？ -我猜2萬
Joey,it is an auction. You don't guess. You buy!
喬伊，這是拍賣會 你不是猜，是買
What?
什麼？
I don't have $20,000.
我沒有2萬
Congratulations on your new boat, Joey Tribbiani.
恭喜你購得新船… 喬伊崔比亞尼
Joey,sit down.
坐下啦
Forget her. You enjoy this.
別理她，開心就好
What are you doing?
你在幹什麼？
"One nation...
一個國家
under God,indivisible, with liberty and justice for all."
在神之下 不可分割，全民擁有 自由公正
I remembered it. The champagne is here.
我記得是這樣背，香檳來了
-You okay? -Yes. I'm good. Are you good?
-你沒事吧？ -我很好，你好嗎？
Is everything..? Are you perfect?
這一切…你很好嗎？
Yeah. I'm okay.
還好
Actually,I'm a bit cold. Can I have your jacket?
其實我有點冷 外套可以借我嗎？
No, you can't have my jacket.
不行，我的外套不能借你
Because then I would be cold.
因為那樣我就會冷
If you thought you'd be cold, you should've brought a jacket.
你要是覺得會冷 應該自己帶外套
But, other than that, are you okay?
除此之外你好嗎？
-Are you sure you're okay? -Yes. I'm fine.
-你真的沒事嗎？ -對，我很好
In fact,I've been fine for a long time now and I think...
我這段日子一直都很好 我覺得…
the reason is you.
都是因為有你
That's sweet.
好甜蜜喔
Before I met you, I had really little life.
認識你之前 我的人生微不足道
-And I couldn't imagine growing old.. -Oh,my God.
-我無法想像一個人… -我的天哪
-I know. But let me say it. -Richard.
-我知道，不過讓我說完  -理查
What? I'm Chandler.
什麼？我是錢德
Oh, that's Richard.
那是理查
Maybe he won't see us. Richard!
也許他會沒看見 理查
Monica. Chandler.
摩妮卡，錢德
I don't know why I did that.
我不知道我為什麼要抱你
-Good to see you. -You too. You let your hair grow.
-見到你真好 -彼此彼此，你把頭髮留長了
That's right. You always wanted me to.
沒錯，你一直希望我留長
-I see your mustache is back. -Well,my nose got lonely.
-你又開始留鬍子了 -我的鼻子感到寂寞
You don't have a mustache, which is good.
你沒留鬍子，很好
Chandler. I make jokes when I'm uncomfortable.
我是錢德，我一蹩扭就開玩笑
-Hi,I'm Lisa. -Hi.
我是麗莎
I'm sorry. Lisa, Monica, Chandler. We used to date.
抱歉，麗莎 摩妮卡，錢德 我們交往過
Richard, no one's supposed to know about us.
理查，我們的事應該保密
See? I did it again.
我又來了
-Chandler,sit down. -I'll sit down.
-錢德，我們坐下吧 -好，我坐
-Good to see you. -Your table's ready,sir.
-很高興見到你  -您的桌子準備好了
Good to see you guys.
很高興遇見你們
If you prefer,this table's available.
這一桌也是空的
That might be fun.
一起坐應該不錯
-What were you thinking? -I didn't know it was an auction.
你在想什麼？ 我不知道這是拍賣會
I figured I'd take a guess. Help a charity. Free boat!
我以為是猜一猜 幫助慈善團體，免費得帆船
Why would a charity give away a boat?
慈善團體為什麼要送帆船？
I don't know. Charity?
我哪知，做慈善嗎？
Well,just buy the damn boat.
你就買吧
Don't you think you've had enough to drink?
菲比，你喝得夠多了吧？
I'm just helping the kids.
我只是在幫助兒童
How is you drinking helping the kids?
你喝酒怎麼能幫助兒童？
Because the more I drink, the less there is for the kids to drink.
我喝得越多 孩子們能喝的就越少
Mr. Tribbiani, your contribution brings us...
崔比亞尼先生 你的慷慨解囊
a step closer to building the youth center.
讓興建活動中心的事大有進展
-I'm so happy you brought him. -So am I.
-我很高興你帶他來 -我也是
I'm curious. How much is that boat worth?
我很好奇，那艘船值多少？
-I think it was valued at 19,000. -Hey,I was pretty close.
-差不多是1萬9  -我猜得蠻準的
So,bad news.
壞消息
I can't buy the boat. I don't have any money.
我不能買那艘船，我沒有錢
Joey! Joey, good one. He's silly.
喬伊，你真幽默
Good! Very good!
你真會演
-So I think I'm gonna take off now. -You can't leave,Joey!
-好吧，我要閃了 -你不能走，喬伊
You agreed to buy that boat. It's a contract.
你答應要買船，具有約束力
Plus,if you leave, my boss will kill me.
而且你走了 我的主管會宰了我
I don't have that kind of money.
那怎麼辦？我沒有那麼多錢
I know. Okay,okay. This is what we'll do.
我知道，好 好 這樣吧
We'll let the next highest bidder buy it.
我們去找出價第二高的人 然後讓他們去買
Then you'll pay the difference.
你只要付差價
Okay. I don't know why the kids need a youth center anyway.
好 這些小孩要活動中心幹嘛
They should just watch TV after school like I did. I turned out fine.
放了學跟我一樣看電視就好了 我現在也蠻好的
Not great.
但是不優秀
I'm helping the kids so much I think I'm gonna throw up.
我幫助貧童幫到想吐
So we're hiding in the bathroom...
我們躲在洗手間裡
I get out. But before she can, her parents come in.
然後我溜出來 但摩妮卡還沒出來 她父母就進去了
I hide in the shower. They start going at it on the floor.
於是我躲到浴簾後面 接著他們就在地上做起來了
Oh, my God!
我的天哪
I got a good one.
我有一個，我有一個
I once walked in on both my parents making love to the same guy.
我有一次撞見我父母 跟同一個男人做愛
It's so great seeing you guys again. I'd like to make a toast.
遇見你們真的好開心 我想敬酒
As a poet once said, "In the sweetness of friendship...
正如一位詩人所說 「在友誼的甜蜜裡」
Let there be laughter and sharing of pleasures.
「盡情歡笑，分享歡樂吧」
In the dew of little things, the heart finds its morning and is refreshed."
「人心正是從中獲得朝氣 煥然一新」
What?
什麼？
Oh,my God! You guys!
天哪，你們
Have we got a story for you. Guess who we bumped into?
在你開口之前，我們有事要說 猜我們吃飯時遇見誰？
-Who? -Richard!
誰？ 理查
Right, that's Richard's favorite place too.
沒錯，那裡也是理查的最愛
-Oh,you knew that? Good. -Weren't you going out with Elizabeth?
所以你知道？很好 你不是要跟伊麗莎白約會？
I was. She was a little busy with a water balloon fight.
沒錯，但是她忙著打水球仗
Sometimes grownups have commitments they can't get out of.
有時大人就是會有事無法脫身
Maybe she is too young for me.
也許她真的太年輕了
When I was over there, I felt like I was a babysitter.
當我看到她跟朋友橫衝直撞 我覺得我好像保姆
I see what you were talking about. I don't know what to do.
我終於開始瞭解你們的話 我不知道該怎麼辦
Weigh the good stuff about her against the bad.
你可以比較這段感情的利弊
That's what I did when I first started... weighing stuff.
我當初就是這樣…比較東西的
Okay, bad stuff. I'm 12 years older than she is.
好，弊 我比她大12歲
The school could fire you.
學校發現會開除你
-She's leaving for three months. -For camp.
她要離開3個月 去參加夏令營
Okay, good stuff.
好，利
Well,she's sweet and pretty and..
她很甜很漂亮…
And the sex is probably great, huh?
性愛方面很贊吧？
It's tender and respectful, if that's what you mean.
如果你是指很溫柔又互相尊重
The only thing you need to ask is, "Do you see a future?"
你只需要問你自己 你看得見未來嗎？
Do you see yourself marrying her?
你能想像跟她結婚嗎？
My God. You married her, didn't you?
天哪，你已經娶她了對不對？
No, I didn't do that. It's just...
沒有啦，我只是…
Okay, honestly, no. I don't see a big future with her.
好吧，我覺得我們沒什麼未來
Okay, I think that's your answer.
那這就是你的答案了
I gotta talk to her. I hate this part.
我得告訴她 我最恨這個步驟了
Forget Elizabeth. If you're not careful...
你必須忘記伊麗莎白 你要是不小心
you may not get married at all this year.
今年可能會結不到婚
-Weren't you supposed to do something? -Good luck with Elizabeth,my man.
-你今晚不是要做某件事？ -祝分手順利
My God, Phoebe, how many have you had?
天哪，菲比，你喝了幾杯？
1,2,3... Seven times three.. 21!
一，二，三… 七乘以三，二十一杯
-You must be just wasted! -I'm a little tired.
-你一定醉翻了 -是有點累
-Next highest bidder is at table one. -Great.
出價第二高的人在一號桌 太好了
The guy with the Paris trip is at table four.
標到巴黎之旅的人坐四號桌
-Why do you care about who won? -It's a trip for two.
你幹嘛管誰贏得巴黎之旅？ 那是雙人之旅
Excuse me.
失陪
Is the person who won the Paris trip at this table?
抱歉，標到巴黎之旅的人 在這一桌嗎？
-That was me. -Enchante.
我就是 真迷人
-Is there a Mr. Bowmont at this table?  -That's me.
抱歉，有沒有一位波芒先生？ 我就是
Well,hello. This is your lucky day, Mr. Bowmont.
你好 你今天走運了，波芒先生
The Gentleman Daysailer has become available again...
那艘帆船又要賣了
and I believe you made a bid of $18,000.
你開了1萬8的價格
You have to pay that. It's not just a guess.
你得付錢，不是猜好玩的
I was relieved I didn't win. My wife would've killed me.
我沒標到船還鬆了一口氣 我老婆會宰了我
You kidding? She'll love this boat!
不會吧？她會愛死這艘船
-What is your wife's name? -Pam.
尊夫人芳名？ 她叫潘
Just imagine this: The Pam.
只要想像一下 「潘之號」
I don't think she'd like that.
我想她不會喜歡
Okay. Imagine this: The Mr. Bowmont.
那想像…「波芒先生號」
-I don't think so. -Let me paint you a little picture.
還是不要了 讓我為你描繪一下
You are setting sail up the Hudson. You've got the wind in your... arms.
你在哈德遜河上航行 風吹過你的頭…雙手
You get all that peace and quiet you've always wanted.
你得到你企盼已久的安寧
You get back to nature. You can go fishing.
你回到大自然懷抱 你可以釣魚
You get one of those hats. People call you captain.
你可以買一頂帽子 讓大家叫你船長
And then when you're old, Cappy.
等你老了就是老船長
-It's for a good cause. All right. -No way! It's mine!
-管他的，不買說不過去 我買了 -你別想，船是我的
What?
什麼？
-The stuff you said,I want that! -But you don't have $20,000!
-你剛才說的那些事我也要 -但是喬伊，你沒有2萬
Who cares? I'll make payments! I want the Mr. Bowmont!
管他的，我分期，怎樣都好 我要「波芒先生號」
-Oh,my God. You're back. -Let me see it. Let me see your hand.
-天哪，你們回來了 -讓我看你的手，讓我看你的手
Why do you wanna see my hand?
你為什麼要看我的手？
I wanna see what's in your hand. I wanna see the trash.
我想看你手上拿的垃圾
It's all dirty. You should throw this out.
好髒，你最好拿去扔
-What did you just do? -What happened?
你們搞什麼？ 怎麼回事？
-Richard was there. I couldn't do it. -Oh,no.
理查也在，我無法開口 不會吧
I was gonna surprise her tomorrow.
我要延到明天，給她驚喜
-Now you've ruined it. -We didn't.
卻被你們破壞了 我們沒有
Who walks in a room and asks to see a person's hands?
誰會一進門就要看別人的手？
A palm reader, a manicurist, a hand doctor...
算命師、修指甲的小姐 手部醫生…
-Glove salesman. -Good one!
手套推銷員 漂亮
This is terrible. What will I do?
真慘，我該怎麼辦？
She only suspects something. So just throw her off the track.
她只是在懷疑，又不是確定 你可以唬她
I'll pretend marriage is the last thing on my mind.
也對，我可以讓她覺得 我完全不考慮結婚
Yeah! Convince her you're scared of commitment, that you're a coward.
沒錯，讓她相信你很害怕承諾 讓她相信你有點孬種
I can do that. I've had years of practice.
我做得到，我練了30年
Being you is finally gonna pay off!
你這個人總算有價值了
Some idiot keeps stuffing the trash chute with pizza boxes.
某個白癡小孩老是用披薩盒 把垃圾槽堵住
That guy is still doing that?
那個傢伙還是沒改？
Oh,my God. Let me see your hand!
天哪，你們回來了 我看看你的手
You're too late! She already took out the trash!
來不及了 她已經把垃圾拿去扔了
Look,Elizabeth, we have to talk.
伊麗莎白，我們得談一談
I have never had such a healthy breakup.
我跟別人分手沒這麼平和過
She was such a grownup about it.
她表現得好成熟
She didn't seem too immature for me.
我覺得她一點也不幼稚
Did I just make a huge mistake?
我是不是犯了個大錯？
Ross! Wait!
羅斯，等等
Elizabeth, thank God. I was just thinking about..
伊麗莎白，太好了 我正在想說…
You suck!
你最爛了
What?
什麼？
Breakup's still on.
好，分手還是有效
Here she comes. Do I look like I don't wanna get married?
她來了 我像不像不想結婚的人？
And, also, a little like a French guy.
像，還有點像法國人
I never noticed that before.
我第一次發現
-What are you up to? -Hanging out. Talking about websites.
你們在幹什麼？ 只是在殺時間，聊網站
We saw this interesting website about marriage...
有一個網站在討論婚姻...
and how unnecessary it is, a way for the government to keep tabs.
及婚姻的一無是處 說那只是政府監視你的方式
Yeah, Big Brother.
是啊，專制
That's a bit crazy.
有點誇張
Although I am glad you're looking at other things on the lnternet.
不過你們總算上了 其他類別的網站
Got me thinking. Why would anybody want to get married?
不過我就想 為什麼會有人想要結婚？
To celebrate the relationship, solidify the commitment...
為什麼？因為要讚頌這段感情 要鞏固你們的承諾
declare your love for one another to the world.
要向全世界宣佈你們的愛
Well,that's good to know.
能知道你的反應真好
The Mr. Bowmont is here!
「波芒先生號」來了
A diner wants to compliment you. Shall I let him in?
有一位客人想向主廚致意 要讓他進來嗎？
Sure. I love this part.
當然，我最愛這種事了
-Come on in. -Hi.
進來吧
-Richard. -I'm not here to compliment the chef.
理查  其實我不是來向主廚致意的
I hate when people come back to compliment the chef.
沒關係 我最討厭客人跑來致意
Like I have nothing better to do.
好像我很閒似的
So,what's up?
你有什麼事？
It was great seeing you the other night.
那天晚上遇見你很開心
Good to see you too.
我也很開心
-You came to tell me that? -I came to tell you something else.
你就是來說這個的？ 不是，我是來說別的
I came here to tell you I still love you.
我是來說我仍然愛你
What? What did you..? What?
什麼？你剛才…什麼？
I still love you.
我仍然愛你
I know I shouldn't even be here telling you this.
我知道我甚至不該告訴你
You're with Chandler, who I like.
你跟錢德在一起，我很喜歡他
If you say he's straight, I'll believe you.
你說他是異性戀，我就相信你
After seeing you, I knew if I didn't tell you I'd regret it.
但見到你之後 我知道我不說會後悔一輩子
Letting you go was the stupidest thing I ever did.
放棄你是我所做過最蠢的事
You're really not supposed to be back here.
你不該到廚房來的
I'm sorry. I know this is the wrong time and the wrong place...
對不起, 我知道時機地點都不對...
but I had to tell you.
但是我一定要說
I wanna spend my life with you. I wanna marry you.
我想跟你共度一生，我想娶你
I wanna have kids with you.
我想跟你生兒育女
Oh,my God. Why don't they put chairs back here?
這裡為什麼沒擺椅子？
Look,I know this is crazy, but am I too late?
我知道我很扯 已經來不及了嗎？
You're too late. Where was all this three years ago?
沒錯 你3年前怎麼不說這些話？
I know. I was an idiot.
我知道，我是個白癡
I tried to forget you. I really did.
我也想忘記你，真的
After our last lunch, I spent six months in Africa trying to forget.
我們去年吃完飯 我跑去非洲6個月想忘記你
-What did you do there? -Work with blind kids.
你去非洲做什麼？ 幫助盲童
What are you doing to me?
你折磨我嘛
Look,I...
I'm sorry, but this is not gonna happen.
很抱歉，我們之間是不可能的
That's fine. I'll walk away. I'll never bother you again.
好，我會離開 再也不會來煩你
Only if you say Chandler's willing to give you everything I am.
但前提是 錢德也願意給你這一切
Well,he is. I mean...
他願意
marriage is all he talks about. My goodness!
沒錯，他成天把婚姻掛在嘴邊
In fact, I'm the one making him wait.
事實上是我在讓他等
You are? Why?
是嗎？ 對
Why?
為什麼？
Because of the government.
因為政府的陰謀
Isn't it incredible?
很棒吧？
Monica and Chandler are getting married.
摩妮卡和錢德要結婚了
I know. They'll be so happy together.
就是啊，他們會很幸福
How often do two best friends fall in love?
兩個最要好的朋友墜入愛河 這種機率有多大？
-Not that often. -No.
並不太大 沒錯
-I'm so happy for them. -Me too. So happy for them.
我好替他們開心 我也是，好開心
I'm so happy and not at all jealous.
我很高興，毫無嫉妒之心
Oh,no! God, definitely not jealous.
沒錯，當然沒有
I'm probably 98% happy and maybe 2% jealous.
我可能是98%開心 2%嫉妒
-I mean,what's 2%? That's nothing. -Totally.
2%等於沒有 沒錯
-I'm like 90/10. -Yeah. Me too.
我是九比一 我也是
Have you guys seen Chandler?
你們有見到錢德嗎？
No. But you know who was looking for you?
沒有，但你知道誰來找過你？
Tennille.
坦妮爾 （「船長與坦妮爾」為樂團）
The marriage stuff you were saying yesterday? You don't believe that.
你昨天說的那些話 應該不是真心話吧？
Sure,I do. In fact,I think the concept of marriage is unnatural.
當然是 事實上我覺得婚姻本身 就很不近人情
Look at pigs. Let's take a second here and look at pigs.
你看豬嘛，我們來看一下豬
Pigs don't mate for life.
豬不會有固定配偶
A pig can have 100 sexual partners in a lifetime.
豬的一生可以有一百個性伴侶
That's an ordinary pig, not even a pig that's good at sports.
那還只是普通的豬 而不是擅長運動的豬
Yeah, but that's pigs, not people.
對，但那是豬不是人
If marriage worked,I'd be for it. Do you know the divorce rate?
如果結婚行得通，我絕對支持 但是你知道美國的離婚率嗎？
Ninety-seven percent!
97%
Wait a minute.
等一下
Are you telling me you may never want to get married?
你是說你可能永遠都不想結婚
-Who's to say? -You! You are to say!
誰曉得？ 你啊，你曉得
Never say never, but, probably...
話不能說死，不過應該是…
yeah, never.
永遠不會
Oh,my God. Then what are we even doing? What is this?
天哪，那我們在幹什麼？ 現在算什麼？
Whoa,whoa,whoa! What is all this pressure?
幹嘛對我施壓？
Is this some new strategy?
這是某種新策略嗎？
Why don't you put down your copy of The Rules, huh, mantrap?
你別再搞爾虞我詐那一套了
You know what? I gotta go.
你知道嗎？我要走了
It's okay. I got a plan.
放心，我自有打算
-We're gonna find love. -Definitely.
我們會找到真愛的 一定會的
Yeah,I'm pretty confident about that.
我對這點有信心
That's what makes it so easy to be 80% happy for Monica and Chandler.
所以我可以有八成 替摩妮卡和錢德高興
-A guarantee would be nice. -What do you mean?
不過要是有保障就好了 什麼意思？
Some friends make a deal.
有些人不是會跟朋友約定
Like if neither of them are married by 40, they marry each other.
要是兩個人到了40都沒結婚 他們就要結婚
-A backup? -Exactly.
你是指備胎？ 沒錯
Yeah, I've got that.
我已經找好了
You do?
你找好了？
-Who? -Joey.
是誰？ 喬伊
-Joey? Are you serious? -I locked him in years ago.
喬伊？真的還假的？ 我好幾年前就鎖定他了
Wait. So if neither of you are married by 40, you'll marry Joey?
所以要是你們40歲還沒結婚 你就要嫁給喬伊
Yep. We shook on it.
對，我們握手為定
But believe me, that is not how he wanted to seal the deal.
不過他可不想就此打住
Oh, seriously?
是嗎？
I think his exact words were..
對，他說的是…
Charming.
真迷人
He's just a backup.
只是個備胎
-Hey,Monica. -Have you seen Rachel? Or a mirror?
-摩妮卡 -你有見到瑞秋嗎？或是鏡子？
-It's for my boat. Pretty cool,huh? -Yeah,it's great.
-這是我的船長裝，酷吧？ -很酷
What's wrong? Talk to the captain.
怎麼了？告訴船長
Just realizing I'm in a dead-end relationship.
我又發現這段感情是死路一條
-Chandler being difficult? -I don't want marriage tomorrow.
錢德欺負你是吧？ 我又不是明天就要結婚
But I wanna know we're going somewhere, that I'm not wasting time.
我只是想知道 我不是在原地打轉，浪費時間
-You know Chandler. -No,I don't know Chandler.
你也瞭解錢德  我已經不瞭解錢德了
Not anymore. It's like something's changed.
彷彿有什麼事變了
-Maybe you changed. -I didn't change.
也許是你變了？ 我才沒變
Maybe that's the problem.
也許問題就在這裡
-What? -Chandler is a complex fellow.
什麼？ 錢德很複雜
One who is unlikely to take a wife.
不太可能成親
Is that some kind of boat talk?
這是跑船人的用語嗎？
I haven't totally decided how to talk on my boat yet.
我還沒想好在船上的說話風格
Does he think I'll wait around for nothing?
他以為我會空等下去嗎？
Face it. Chandler is against marriage.
面對現實吧，錢德反對婚姻
And always will be.
他是不會變了
There's some people who do wanna marry me.
有些人可是真心想娶我
-There are? -Yeah. Richard.
有嗎？ 有，理查
Richard said he wants to marry you?
理查說他想娶你？
-And Chandler says he hates marriage? -That's right.
錢德說他痛恨婚姻？ 沒錯
Chandler loves marriage!
錢德熱愛婚姻
You just said he hates marriage!
你剛才說他痛恨婚姻
"He's a complex fellow who's unlikely to take a wife"!
說他很複雜，不太可能娶妻
"He's against marriage and always will be"!
說他會永遠反對婚姻
You got that from what I said?
你的解讀是這樣？
After the Cretaceous Period, the dinosaurs were gone.
白堊紀結束，恐龍也從此絕跡
What happened,you guys?
你們究竟怎麼了？
-Rach. -Hey,you.
瑞秋 帥哥
-Come on in. -Thank you.
請進 謝謝
I'm so sorry to hear about you and Elizabeth.
很遺憾你跟伊麗莎白分手了
Thanks. I really thought we'd be able to make it work.
謝謝，我以為我們能克服萬難
I guess it wasn't meant to be.
這大概是命中注定的
Yeah. Love. It's a tricky business,isn't it?
是啊，愛情…愛情真是微妙
-I guess so. -So,what do you say we make a pact?
是啊  我們要不要來做個約定
If you and I are both single by 40, we get married.
要是我們到了40都還沒結婚 我們就結婚
I mean,we know each other, we like each other...
我們互相認識，互相喜歡
we've already slept together, so there'll be no surprises.
我們已經上過床，不會有意外
No, like, "What's that?"
不會覺得「搞什麼？」
-Oh,you want me to be your backup. -Exactly.
你想找我當備胎？ 沒錯
Yeah. I already have one.
我已經有備胎了
-What? Who? -Phoebe.
是誰？ 菲比
Phoebe?
菲比？
But she just said Joey is her backup.
但是她說喬伊是她的備胎
Oh,I don't think so.
才不是呢
We just spoke. She said that she and Joey made a deal.
羅斯，我剛跟她聊過 她說她和喬伊約好了
That's impossible. We have had a deal for years. We shook on it.
不可能的，我們早就約好了 還握手為定
Although, believe me, she wanted to do a lot more than that.
只不過她覺得握手還不夠…
Gunther, it's Joey. Is Chandler there?
阿甘，我是喬伊，錢德在嗎？
Listen. What kind of muffins do they serve at sea?
我問你，跑船都吃哪一種鬆糕
Where the hell have you been?!
你上哪去了？
I was making a coconut phone with the Professor.
我在跟教授做椰子電話
Richard told Monica he wants to marry her.
理查跟摩妮卡說他想娶她
-What? -I've been trying to find you.
什麼？ 就是啊，我一直想去找你 叫你別玩了
And I would have if these damn boat shoes wouldn't keep flying off!
可是這雙鞋子跑一跑就掉
-Oh,my God! -I know! They suck!
我的天哪  就是啊，爛死了
He's not supposed to ask her to marry him! I am!
他不該向我的女朋友求婚 該求婚的人是我
-I know! -What..?
我知道 那…
You know what I'll do? I'll go over there and kick his ass!
你知道嗎？我要去找他教訓他
Will you help me?
你願意幫忙嗎？
Look, I don't think us getting our asses kicked is a solution, okay?
錢德，被他海扁一頓不是辦法
-Look,just go and find Monica. -You're right.
趕快去找摩妮卡吧  你說得對
Okay. I'm gonna get the ring...
好 我去拿戒指...
I'm gonna go find her and I'm gonna propose!
我要找到她，直接向她求婚
Dude! Dude! Dude!
老兄 怎樣？
That coconut phone might be good for the boat.
你的椰子電話 也許很適合擺在船上
Hi.
I don't know why I'm here.
我不知道我來幹什麼
I didn't ask.
我又沒問
-You wanna come in? -I don't know.
你要進來嗎？ 我不知道
Oh,okay.
好吧
I'll just leave the door open and sit on the couch.
那我把門開著，回去坐下
-Chandler is such an idiot! -Drink?
錢德真是個白癡  喝酒？
-Scotch on the.. -Rocks with a twist?
好，我要威士忌加… 冰塊和萊姆片？
I remember.
我記得
You still smoking cigars?
還在抽雪茄？
No, no. That's art.
沒有，那是藝術
If it bothers you, I can put my art out.
如果你不喜歡 我可以把藝術熄掉
No,that's okay.
沒關係
So, Monica, let me ask you a question.
摩妮卡，我問你一件事
Since we broke up, do you ever...
我們分手後，你有...
think about me?
想過我嗎？
Actually,I thought about you a few months ago.
我2個月前還想到你
-Really? -But it's because...
是嗎？ 不過是因為...
I had an eye exam, and I don't like my new eye doctor.
我去做眼睛檢查 又不喜歡我的新醫生
-Who is it? -Edward Nevsky.
是誰？ 愛德華奈夫斯基
He's no good.
他的確很差
Do you ever think about me...
你有想過...
-in a non-eye-doctor way? -No.
非眼科醫生的我嗎？ 沒有
Because getting over you was the hardest thing I've ever done.
但忘記你是我這輩子最難的事
I never let myself think about you.
我不讓自己想到你
Wow.
Phoebe, you picked Joey and Ross?
菲比 你找了喬伊和羅斯？
-You can't have two backups! -Of course I can.
你不能有兩個備胎 當然可以
It's good sense to back up your backup.
眼光獨到才會替備胎找備胎
-Look, I've already lost Chandler. -What?
我已經折損錢德了 什麼？
Hey, Phoebe! We're both your backup?
菲比，我們都是你的備胎？
How could you do this to me?
菲比，你怎麼可以這樣？
Why are you complaining? You were both aware of the situation.
我不知道你們在抱怨什麼 你們都知道這個狀況
-I was not! -No,we weren't!
我們不知道 我不知道
This kind of backtalk won't fly when we're married.
婚後你們可不能這樣頂嘴
You can't have both. Pick one.
菲比，你不能獨佔他們 你得選一個
-Pick me! -No,pick me!
選我 不，選我
-I don't wanna end up an old maid. -All right. Well,let's see.
-我不想當老處女  -好吧，我看看
Ross is a good father.
羅斯是個好爸爸
But...
但是...
Joey has a boat. This is hard.
喬伊有船，好難選喔
This is crazy. I wanna switch to Rachel.
太扯了，我要換成瑞秋
-I wanna switch to Rachel too. -No,wait. Just wait.
我也要換成瑞秋  不，等一下
Wait,guys. Don't make any rash decisions.
你們別急著做決定
Just remember my promise:
記得我的承諾吧？
If we get married,three times a week.
結婚之後 1星期三次
Oh,my God. Phoebe...
天哪，菲比
I'm talking about massages.
我是說按摩
No,I'm not.
I know how to settle it. We'll do this.
我知道該怎麼解決了 辦法就是
I'm gonna write "Joey" on one napkin...
我在一張紙巾上寫喬伊
and "Ross" on the other napkin and we're gonna pick one.
一張紙巾上寫羅斯 然後我們一人抽一張
That person will be our backup. Okay?
那個人就是我們的備胎  好嗎？
-Sounds fair. -All right.
很公平 那好
Good. Switching them up.
好，我來弄亂
-Pick one. -Left.
選一邊 左邊
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
謝謝 不客氣
-Ross. -Joey.
羅斯 喬伊
-We should switch. -Absolutely.
我們交換好了 沒錯
I missed you, you ugly flat-faced old freak.
我想念你 丑不啦嘰的扁臉老怪物
Excuse me?
你說什麼？
Him.
他啦
I missed this apartment. Now, this is a grownup's apartment.
我想念這間房子 這才是大人的房子
I should be with a grownup, you know?
我應該跟大人在一起，你懂吧
You're saying you need to be with someone more mature.
你是說 你要跟比較成熟的人在一起
Maybe someone with...
也許是一個…
a license to practice medicine.
有醫師執照的人
Or a mustache.
或是有鬍子的人
Let's face it. I'm not a kid anymore.
說真的，我不是小孩子了
I need someone who wants the same things.
我需要一個目標相同的人
Coming to my work and telling me you love me, I want that!
來我工作的地方跟我示愛 我要的是那樣
Talking about pig sex over lunch, I don't want that!
吃飯時聊豬的性愛 我不要那樣
I think that's fair.
很公平
Fair? Please, don't even talk to me about fair.
公平？別跟我提公平
Fair would've been you wanting to marry me then.
公平的意思是你當年想娶我
Or Chandler wanting to marry me now.
或是錢德現在想娶我
Believe me,nothing about this is fair. Nothing.
這整件事一點也不公平
-Nothing! Nothing! -It's okay.
不公平不公平不公平… 別激動
Nothing.
不公平
I don't know.
我不知道
I know.
我知道
I have to figure some..
我得先...
Some stuff,before I can...
把事情想清楚 然後才能…
I understand.
我懂
Take as much time as you want.
你只管慢慢想
Ten, even 20 minutes, if you need it.
10分鐘、20分鐘都行
I'll be here. Not smoking.
我會在這裡，不會抽煙
Where is she?
她人呢？
I'm not scared of you.
我可不怕你
She's not here. And please come in.
她不在，請進
Scotch on the rocks...
威士忌加冰和萊姆片
with a twist, on a coaster.
放在杯墊上？
Monica?
摩妮卡，摩妮卡
Okay, she was here. But she left.
好吧，她來過，又走了
Where did she go?
她去哪裡？
She said she had to think things over.
她說她要想清楚
Oh,my God. I can't believe this. I thought you were a good guy.
天哪，我真不敢相信 我以為你是個好人
Look,nothing happened.
我們又沒怎樣？
Nothing? So you didn't tell my girlfriend you love her?
沒怎樣？那你沒和我女朋友示愛？
Well, all right, one thing happened.
好吧，只有這樣
You know what you did? My girlfriend is thinking things over.
我真不敢相信 你知道你做了什麼？ 我的女朋友在想事情
You made my girlfriend think!
你讓我的女朋友思考
Well,I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
-What's to think about? I love her. -Well...
她還需要想什麼？我愛她
I'm willing to offer her things that you aren't.
我願意給她你不願意給的東西
I'm willing to offer her those things. I had a plan...
但是我願意給 我只是故意...
to throw her off so when I offered all these things,she'd be surprised.
要讓她失望 等真相大白，她就會很驚喜
If it helps, it worked very well.
那效果真的很好
It was working till you showed up, you big tree.
直到你殺出來，水泥牆
This isn't fair.
這樣不公平
You had your chance with her, and you blew it!
你曾經有機會，結果你搞砸了
This is my chance. I won't blow it, because we are meant for each other.
現在輪到我了，我不會搞砸 因為我們是天生一對
And this has all just been one stupid mistake!
而這一切只是個愚蠢的錯誤
I was gonna propose tonight.
我本來打算今晚求婚的
-You were gonna propose? -Yeah,I even...
你要求婚？ 對，我還…
got a ring. Did you get a ring?
準備了戒指，你有嗎？
No, I don't have a ring.
沒有，我沒準備
You go get her, Chandler.
你去找她吧，錢德
And can I give you a piece of advice?
我可以給你一個忠告嗎？
If you do get her...
要是你得到了她
don't let her go.
一定要好好把握
Trust me.
相信我
You know, Richard, you are a good guy.
理查…你的確是個好人
I know.
我知道
I hate that.
真討厭
-I've gotta find Monica. -She's gone.
待會再說，我得去找摩妮卡 她走了
-What? -She had a bag and she left.
-什麼？ -她走了，提著一個包包走了
-What? -She was all crying...
-什麼？ -她哭得很傷心
She said you guys want different things.
說你們要的東西不一樣
-Why didn't you stop her? Why didn't you tell her it was a plan? -I told her everything.
-說她需要時間思考 你為什麼不攔住她？ 不說出我的打算？ -我都說了
-But she wouldn't believe me. -Well,where..? Where did she go?
-但是她不信  -那她…她上哪去了？
To her parents'. She said you shouldn't call. But if I were you,I would.
她父母家，她叫你不要打給她 不過要是我就會打
-I can't believe I ruined this. -I am so sorry,man.
我居然搞砸了 我很遺憾
You wanted it to be a surprise.
你希望是個驚喜的
Oh,my God.
天哪
Chandler...
錢德…
in all my life...
我這輩子…
I never thought I would be so lucky...
從來沒想過我會這麼幸運
as to fall in love with my best...
可以…愛上我最要好的…
My best...
我最要好的…
There's a reason why girls don't do this! Okay, okay, okay.
所以說都是男人求婚嘛 好好好
I'll do it. I thought...
我來，我以為…
Wait, I can do this.
等等，我一定行
I thought that it mattered...
我以為...
what I said or where I said it.
開口的時間地點很重要
Then I realized...
後來才發現...
the only thing that matters is that you...
唯一重要的是你…
You make me happier than I ever thought I could be.
讓我得到超乎想像的幸福
And if you let me...
所以如果你願意
I'll spend all my life trying to make you feel the same way.
我願意用下半生 讓你跟我一樣幸福
Monica...
摩妮卡…
will you marry me?
你願意嫁給我嗎？
Yes.
我願意
I knew you were likely to take a wife!
我就知道你應該會成親
Can we come in yet? We're dying out here!
可以進去了嗎？我們快憋死了
Come in! Come in!
進來，進來
We're engaged!
我們訂婚了
This is the least jealous I've ever been.
這是我最不嫉妒的時候
Oh, no, wait! This is wrong! Ross isn't here!
等等，不行啦，羅斯不在
Hell, he's done it three times. He knows what it's about!
他都玩三次了 知道是怎麼回事